Finding aid to Caroline Heminway Kierstead papers CA.MA.140 ======= Finding aid to Caroline Heminway Kierstead papers CA.MS.00140 >>>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22
Smith College Archives
Caroline Heminway Kierstead papers
1923-1985
Smith College Archives
Kierstead, Caroline Heminway
CA.MA.140
CA.MS.00140
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
This collection documents the research insterests, professional career and personal life of Caroline Heminway Kierstead, a professor of geology at Smith College. Materials include correspondence, publications, diaries, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Caroline Heminway Kierstead was a professor of Geology at Smith College as well as an internationally known breeder and exhibitor of Pembroke Welsh Corgi dogs. Born in Corning, New York on July 12, 1904 to Herbert A. and Ella May (Daley) Heminway, Kierstead graduated from Mount Holyoke College in 1925 with a major in Philosophy and Psychology, and a minor in Geology. After working in her father's law office for a year, she returned to school to earned a master's degree from Cornell University (1928) and later a Ph.D. from Indiana University (1941). She also studied over the years at Syracuse University, the University of Colorado, and the University of Wyoming. Heminway married Friend H. Kierstead, an electrical engineer from Pittsfield, Massachusetts, in 1947. He died around 1970.
Kierstead joined the faculty of Smith's Geology Department in 1928 and retired after a long teaching career in 1969. She was promoted steadily through the department, from instructor when she began in 1928, to assistant professor (1932), associate professor (1940) and finally full professor in 1964. Elected chairman of the Geology Department in February 1946, Kierstead served in that capacity until January 1952. She also acted for a short time as the Dean of the Class of 1944. From 1943 to 1945 she took a leave of absence to work for Shell Oil Company, bringing along two Smith graduates. This experience gave her a useful understanding of the oil industry.
Keirstead was interested in many fields of geology, and was especially partial to topological and geological maps. Her field of research was micropaleontology, specifically the study of foraminifera, or unicellular shelled microorganisms. Her publications include many articles for scientific journals, one book, and a textbook; she also edited and contributed to several other publications. Her geological research led her to travel all over the world, including Antarctica and New Zealand. Additionally, she held memberships in many prestigious professional associations.
In her private life, Kierstead was an internationally known breeder and exhibitor of Pembroke Welsh Corgi dogs. Her dogs won several American Kennel Club champions. She served as president of the Pembroke Welsh Corgi Club of America for a period of time, and belonged to several other dog clubs as well. Also, she published Pembroke Pictures and Pedigree, an annotated index of the history of the breed. Kierstead died on June 17, 1985 at the age of 80.
Scope and Contents
The Caroline Heminway Kierstead Papers, 1923-1985, consist of 2.5 linear feet of materials materials related to the professional and personal life of a long-time member of the Smith College Geology Department. Types of materials include correspondence, publications, handwritten and typescript lecture and research notes, diaries, and photographs. These items not only document her teaching career at Smith and her research interests, but also provide insight into her personal life and pastimes. Her detailed lecture notes and course material give researchers an informative look at the Geology Department curriculum and methods in the middle of the twentieth century.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series:
SERIES I: BIOGRAPHY
SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III: COURSE MATERIALS
SERIES IV: LECTURE NOTES
SERIES V: NOTES
SERIES VI: WRITINGS
Related Material
See RG 52. Academic Departments for information on the Geology Department.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated by Marion H. Nutting, Kierstead's sister, in 1985.
Geology; Geology-Curriculum; Geology-Study and Teaching (Higher); Micropaleontology; Science-History; United States-Intellectual Life; Women Geologists; Shell Oil
- SERIES I: BIOGRAPHY
  Scope and Contents of the Collection
  Provides background information on Caroline Kierstead's life and overall academic and professional careers.
  - Biography, 1928-1985 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">1)
  - Geology Courses - Cornell, 1926-28 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">2)
  - Geology Courses - Indiana University, 1938 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">3)
  - Geology Courses - Mount Holyoke, 1923 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">4)
  - Geology Courses - University of Wyoming, 1934 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">5)
- SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE
  Contains both personal and professional letters to and from Kierstead. She appears to have had a close relationship with her father, who wrote nearly every week in her early years at Smith.
  - Family, 1928-51 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">6)
  - Friends, 1961 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">7)
  - Personal - Dogs, 1973 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">8)
  - Personal - Investments, 1961 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">9)
  - Professional, 1931-68 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">10)
  - Professional - Geology Department, 1950-69 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">11)
  - Professional - Sale of Library, 1985 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">12)
  - Professional - Shell Oil, 1943-48 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">13)
  - Professional - Students, 1946-69 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">14)
  - Professional - Field Geology, 1942 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">15)
- SERIES III: COURSE MATERIALS
  Holds materials related to the geology courses she taught at Smith and includes teaching outlines, exams, and student papers. These materials provide a useful glimpse into the department's curriculum.
  - Micropaleontology, 1939-65 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">16)
  - Micropaleontology - Student Papers, 1949-66 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">17)
  - Paleontology, 1929-68 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">18)
  - Senior Review Essay, 1961 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">19)
  - Strategraphy, 1934-63 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">20)
  - Structural Geology, 1941-62 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">21)
  - Exercises Upon Geological Maps, 1937-53 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">22)
  - Senior Field Trip, 1946; 1948 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">23)
  - Student Papers, 1952-64 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">24)
  - Student Papers - Master's Thesis, 1952 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">25)
- SERIES IV: LECTURE NOTES
  Contain handwritten and typed notes and guidelines for lectures and personal research on a wide array of geological topics. (see also SERIES V: NOTES)
  - Caribbean, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">26)
  - Connecticut River Valley Climate, 1967 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">27)
  - English Jurassic, 1951 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">28)
  - Evolution, 1940 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">29)
  - Lesser Autilles, 1938 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">30)
  - Nature of Species, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">31)
  - New Zealand, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">32)
  - Use of Forams, 1954 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">33)
- SERIES V: NOTES
  Contain handwritten and typed notes and guidelines for lectures and personal research on a wide array of geological topics. (see also SERIES IV: LECTURE NOTES)
  - Age of the Earth, 1948-62 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">34)
  - Correlation of Formations, 1958 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">35)
  - Crust of the Earth, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">36)
  - Faults, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">37)
  - Folding, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">38)
  - Geological Maps of New Zealand, 1962 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">39)
  - Jointing, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">40)
  - Jurassic, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">41)
  - Miocene Pelecypods, 1966 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">42)
  - North Wind Forams Project, 1963 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">43)
  - Ostracods, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">44)
  - Physical Characteristics of Rocks, 1951; 1956 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">45)
  - Porifera, 1956 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">46)
  - Radiolaria, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">47)
  - Rock Structures, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">48)
  - Species Problem, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">49)
  - Stromatoporoidea, 1956 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">50)
  - Structural Geology, 1957-59 (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">51)
  - Tertiary, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">52)
  - Thickness of Beds, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">53)
  - Triassic, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">54)
  - Unconformities, undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">55)
  - Photographs, 1927; undated (Box 1, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">56)
- SERIES VI: WRITINGS
  Collects Kierstead's publications, edited books drafts, and a diary.
  - "The Cambrian Stratigraphy of Eastern New York and Western New England, 1935 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">57)
  - Diary, 1961 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">58)
  - Field Report, 1934 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">59)
  - "Foraminifera Manuscript", undated (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">60)
  - Kierstead Revision of Galloway Manual of Foraminifera, 1961 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">61)
  - Kierstead Revision of Galloway Manual of Foraminifera - Draft, undated (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">62)
  - Kierstead Revision of Galloway Manual of Foraminifera, undated (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">63)
  - Manual of Foraminifera Index, 1964 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">64)
  - Master's Thesis, 1928 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">65)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1926; 1943 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">66)
  - New England Geological Conference Guidebook, undated (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">67)
  - Planktonic Conference, 1967 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">68)
  - "Tertiary Foraminifera of Porto Rico", 1941 (Box 2, >>>>>> 9513965d9df0c493d3fef1502b8c9358307d0a22 type="folder">69)